Guide to the Stanford University, Special Services Office, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Special Services Office, records
1967-1973
SC0106
Stanford University. Special Services Office.
6 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, Special Services Office, April 1973, June 1977.
Information about Access
Series I - The use of any personal names is prohibited.
Series II - closed indefinitely unless permission to use is granted by the Dean of Student Affairs. The use of any personal names is prohibited.
Series III - open with the following stipulations: no names may be used in any written documents where noted. Where no restrictions are noted, names may be used for publications. Boxes 3 and 4, received in April 1977 are restricted indefinitely.
Series IV - closed indefinitely unless permission to use is granted by the Dean of Student Affairs.
Description of the Collection
Series I - Office records of the Special Services Office. These six boxes contain mainly office correspondence and informative material pertaining to the draft and draft counseling. Also included are 5 volumes of computer printouts of statistical analyses concerning Stanford students and their draft classifications. The order and the titles of the folders in this collection were preserved exactly as they were received in the Archives office. The register contains some information added by the arranger in an attempt to indicate the contents of the file where not clear from its title.
Series II - Files consisting mainly of correspondence relating to named individuals and specific counseling cases. These files were selected to serve as examples and illustrations of the work done by the draft counseling office.
Series III - Files of students who filed for exemption as Conscientious Objectors, their statements, letters of support, and, in some cases, transcripts of their personal appearances.
Series IV - II-S (student deferment classification) files kept for the academic years 1971/72 and 1972/73. These files were received in April 1977.
Access Terms
Stanford University -- General subdivision--Students.;; Stanford University. Special Services Office.; Conscientious objectors.; Draft.
Collection Contents
- Office Files, Series I
  The use of any personal names is prohibited.
  - W. W. Leland: miscellaneous correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous literature and publications for L.S.J.U. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Inter-office memoranda, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mailing list: Deans and department heads (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Student confirmation to state directors, Oct 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Graduate division, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Graduate acceptances declined, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memos to file, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Overseas Campuses, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Overseas Campuses, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with Selective Service System, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Informational material regarding I-S(c) classification (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Literature from the Department of Defense on Conscientious Objectors, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence regarding I-D classification, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence regarding I-D classification, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Information regarding I-Y classification, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Stanford requests for deferments, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Departmental certification, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Graduate student deferment - II-S, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - II-s - undergraduate, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Information regarding aliens and draft, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Information regarding Canada, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Postponement of induction, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Induction, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1967 Draft Act, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - General draft statistics, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Ad Hoc committee on the draft, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Marshall Commission, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    news releases
  - Alternative service, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Medical appeals and information, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Presidential appeal board, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Judicial information, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Congressional Record, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Congressional activity, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - R.O.T.C., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Proposed amendment to S.S.S., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Nixon
  - Draft reform. Proposals and commentaries: current developments., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Business School: MBA-PCV program., 1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Veterans, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Service Information Service
  - Miscellaneous reports on draft effects., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Law School Registration, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Draft classification survey by school, department, and graduating class. Fall, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Report on CONUS Intelligence from Washington Monthly, Jan 1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Draft status of graduate students, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Proposed law, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Operations bulletins (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Newsletters written by General Hershey for Selective Service Boards
  - Manpower Comments, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Information regarding draft calls
  - Literature, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Campus draft activity, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Volunteer Army, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Newspaper articles
  - Orders for Working Paper, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    This paper was published by W. Leland, head counselor of the Special Services Office. This file contains draft and published copy of the pamphlet, and correspondence regarding it
  - Area draft counseling, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Paper: "Draft counseling and estimated impact, 1968-1969" written by William Leland. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Selective Service 1946-1965. (National Service Office) Correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Memoranda from Special Services Office, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Old Selective Service files, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Selective Service Information at other universities., 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - University Committee on Selective Service, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - University Committee on Selective Service, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Clippings on draft, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - R.O.T.C. as campus issue, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - East Palo Alto draft counseling center, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - San Francisco Selective Service Lawyer's Panel, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Dean of Graduate Studies memos, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - University policies and guidelines affecting office of Special Services, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Invoices, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Scientific manpower commission, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Correspondence
  - Memos to departments, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Mountain View Teen Post, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    For C.O. Alternate Service
  - The lottery, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Data on Stanford students, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Impact of draft on Physics Departments (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Survey made in departments of 11 differnt universities
  - Data processing, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Documents related to counseling, 1969-1972 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Special Services Office staffing, 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Civilian work program, 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Dean of Students staff meetings, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Job applicants, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Office memos and bulletins, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Rough draft", 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Stanford Daily draft info. column
  - "Rough draft", 1971 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - I-0, 1964-1970 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Medical Referral Service information sheet (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Minutes of meetings of Stanford Committee on Selective Service, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence of Stanford Committee on Selective Service, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence of Stanford Committee on Selective Service, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Articles pertaining to the Selective Service (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Executive order 11360 - Amending draft regulations, July 4, 1967. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Counseling cases - Fall 1972 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Statistics kept by Special Services office
  - Minutes of local draft counselor meetings, 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - 1973/74 Budget, 1973-1974 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Orders and invoices for books and supplies: 1967-1973 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Special Services Office staff: Job descriptions and division of responsibility., Dec 1969 - June 1972 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Special Services Office (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Handouts giving general information concerning the function of the office and the state of the draft.
  - Dean of Student Affairs memoranda., Dec 1972 - May 1973 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    Memos concern the closure of the draft counselling office, and disposal of its records
  - Zeiss case: 1972. (Box 11, Folder 8)
    Correspondence and arbitrator's report involving salary grievance by a C.O. employed by Stanford University.
  - Selective Service Registrar materials., 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Alan Strain's notes and questions - National Selective Service Conference., Jan 1972 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - San Jose State class: October 1971. (Box 11, Folder 11)
    Materials for a draft counselling class taught by Alan Strain.
  - "Rough Draft", Sep - Dec 1969 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - "Rough Draft", May - Oct 1971 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - "Rough Draft", Jan - Dec 1972 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - "Rough Draft", Jan - April 1973 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with SSS on students and II-S, 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - II-s Deferment for 5-year programs, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence regarding medical students' status with the SSS, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Statistical list of students' draft classifications by department, Fall 1969 (Box 6)
  - Statistical list of students sorted by state and local boards (Box 7)
  - Statistical list of students who have/have not claimed their C.O. with their board (Box 8)
  - Statistical list summarizing student draft classification information (Box 9)
  - Local boards (Box 10)
- Correspondence, Series II
  Closed indefinitely unless permission to use is granted by the Dean of Student Affairs. The use of any personal names is prohibited.
  - Counseling correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Counseling correspondence, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Counseling cases, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Counseling correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Selective Service System, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: Mark Edwards (counselor), 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters in support of C. O.'s written by Alan Strain, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Overseas Campuses, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Support letters: miscellaneous, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Release forms for anonymous files in Series III (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Conscientious Objector Files, Series III
  Open with the following stipulations: no names may be used in any written documents where noted. Where no restrictions are noted, names may be used for publications. Boxes 3 and 4, received in April 1977 are restricted indefinitely.
  - Anonymous (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anonymous (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anonymous (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anonymous (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anonymous (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anonymous (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anonymous (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Anonymous (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Anonymous (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Anonymous (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Anonymous (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Beale, James (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Chambers, Anthony (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Clark, Lyman (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Martin, Anthony (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Russell, Steven Paul (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Shibata, David (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Shippee, John (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Silver, Franklin (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Spaulding, Charles (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Wertheim, Ralph (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Alway, Frederick (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Anderson, H. Lenox (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Arnet, Ned (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chapin, F. Stuart (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Crabbe, John (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Foorman, David (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Kline, Mark (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Locke, Richard (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - MacLaury, Michael (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - McEntyre, John (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - McRae, James (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - McRae, James (Box 2, Folder 11a)
  - Miller, David (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Naylor, D. Keith (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Pederson, Gary (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Perez, Valentin (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Pocekay, Dennis (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Pollard, David (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Pope, Christopher (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - James E. Scarff file (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Daniel George Stone file (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - John S. Stuart file (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Michael D. Thacker file (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Adler, Fred (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Armstrong, Keith (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Barnes, Cecil (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Barre, Allen (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Barstow, David (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bela, James (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Boyd, Richard (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Boyer, Peter (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bursner, John (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Burstein, Leigh (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Buxton, Richard (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Cross, Raymond (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - DeFraties, Terrill (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Dickson, Patrick (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Donnelly, David (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Dumitra, John (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Ellis, Kenneth (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Evans, George (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Fenner, Thomas (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Fishman, Steve (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Frye, Brian (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Gordon, Robert (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Hagemann, Dave (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Hoddle, Dyke (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Himmelright, Ronald (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Holkar, Richard (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Huseby, Irvin (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Jasbard, Lee (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Koch, Steven (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Krieg, Lawrence (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Kroger, Charles (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Lendle, Donald (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Lucas, Kermit (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Lundberg, Mark (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Lush, Ben (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Madison, Curtis (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Mann, Timothy (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Marshall, Frederick (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Martinez, Francisco (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Maysenhalder, Ronald (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Navarro, Jose-Manuel (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Oikawa, Kenneth (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Palerm, Phillip (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Payocchi, Richard (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Poplin, Steven (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Quick, Stephen (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Renner, David (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Rinehart, Marion (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Schnader, Wulf (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Scott, Stephen (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Self, Terry (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Shulman, David (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Simms, Lee (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Smith, Stephen (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Schawrz, Leonard (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Wagner, John (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Walter, Clinton (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Wichert, Geoffrey (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Winston, Leon (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Wolfe, Robert (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Yanski, Clarence (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Student Deferment Files, 1971-1973; Series IV (Box 1)
  Closed indefinitely unless permission to use is granted by the Dean of Student Affairs.
  - II-S Files: 1971/72 A - B, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - II-S Files: 1971/72 C - D, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - II-S Files: 1971/72 E - G, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - II-S Files: 1971/72 H - K, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - II-S Files: 1971/72 L - N, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - II-S Files: 1971/72 O - S, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - II-S Files: 1971/72 T - Z, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - II-S Files: 1972/73 A - F, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - II-S Files: 1972/73 G - M, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - II-S Files: 1972/73 N - S, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - II-S Files: 1972/73 T - Z, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)